Hello, everyone. Because this is my first time at TED,
مرحباً بالجميع. لأن هذه هي أول مرة لي في تيد،
I've decided to bring along an old friend
قررت أن أحضر معي صديقا قديما
to help break the ice a bit.
ليساعدني في كسر الجمود قليلا.
Yes. That's right. This is Barbie.
نعم. هذا صحيح. إنها باربي.
She's 50 years old. And she's looking as young as ever.
تبلغ 50 سنة. وما تزال تبدو يافعة كما كانت.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I'd also like to introduce you to
لكني أرغب في أن أقدم لكم أيضاً
what may be an unfamiliar face.
ما قد يبدو وجهاً غير مألوف.
This is Fulla. Fulla is the Arab world's answer to Barbie.
أنها فُلّة. فُلّة هي إجابة العالم العربي لباربي.
Now, according to proponents of the clash of civilizations,
الآن ، وفقا لأنصار الصدام بين الحضارات ،
Barbie and Fulla occupy these completely separate spheres.
كلا باربي وفُلّة تشغلان هذه الأسافير المختلفة تماماً.
They have different interests. They have divergent values.
لديهما مصالح مختلفة. لديهم قيم متباينة.
And should they ever come in contact ...
ولا ينبغي أن يتواصلا بتاتا...
well, I've got to tell you, it's just not going to be pretty.
حسناً، يجب علي أن أخبركم، لن يكون ذلك جيداً.
My experience, however, in the Islamic world is very different.
لكن تجربتي، في العالم الإسلامي مختلفة جداً.
Where I work, in the Arab region,
حيث أعمل، في المنطقة العربية،
people are busy taking up Western innovations
والناس مشغولون بإستخدام الإبتكارات الغربية
and changing them into things
ويقوموا بتحويلها الى أشياء
which are neither conventionally Western,
التي ليست تقليدية غربية ،
nor are they traditionally Islamic.
ولا تقليدية إسلامية.
I want to show you two examples.
أريد أن أعرض عليكم مثالين.
The first is 4Shbab.
الأول هو "فور شباب".
It means "for youth" and it's a new Arab TV channel.
وتعني " للشباب" وهي قناة تلفزيونية عربية.
(Video): Video clips from across the globe.
(فيديو): مقاطع فيديو من حول العالم.
The USA.
أمريكا.
♫ I am not afraid to stand alone ♫
♫لست خائفاً لأكون لوحدي♫
♫ I am not afraid to stand alone, if Allah is by my side ♫
♫لست خائفاً لأكون لوحدي، إذا كان الله يعينني♫
♫ Everything will be all right ♫
♫كل شئ سيكون بخير ♫
♫ I am not afraid to stand alone ♫
♫لست خائفاً لأكون لوحدي♫
The Arab world.
العالم العربي.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
♫ She was preserved by modesty of the religion ♫
♫تم الحفاظ عليها عبر حياء الدين♫
♫ She was adorned by the light of the Quran ♫
♫ كانت تتزين بنور القرآن ♫
Shereen El Feki: 4Shbab has been dubbed Islamic MTV.
شيرين الفقي: للشباب يسمى ب "أم تي في" الإسلامي.
Its creator, who is an Egyptian TV producer
مؤسسه، الذي هو منتج تلفزيوني مصري
called Ahmed Abu Haïba,
يسمى أحمد أبو هيبة،
wants young people to be inspired
يريد أن يلهم الشباب
by Islam to lead better lives.
بالإسلام من أجل حياة أفضل.
He reckons the best way to get that message across
يعتقد أن أفضل طريقة ليوصل تلك الرسالة
is to use the enormously popular medium of music videos.
عبر إستخدام وسيط موسيقى الفيديو الشائع جداً.
4Shbab was set up as an alternative
للشباب تم تأسيسه كبديل
to existing Arab music channels.
لقنوات الموسيقى العربية الموجودة حالياً.
And they look something like this.
وهي تبدو شيئاً كهذا.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
That, by the way is Haifa Wehbe. She's a Lebanese pop star
هذه، بالمناسبة هيفاء وهبي. وهي نجمة غناء بوب لبنانية
and pan-Arab pin-up girl.
وشابة جذابة وقومية عربية .
In the world of 4Shbab, it's not about bump and grind.
في عالم "للشباب"، الأمر ليس حول اللت والعجن.
But it's not about fire and brimstone either.
ولكنه ليس حول الكبريت والنار أيضاً.
Its videos are intended to show
أنها فيديوهات هدفها هو إظهار
a kinder, gentler face of Islam,
وجه رؤوف، وأكثر لطفاً للإسلام،
for young people to deal with life's challenges.
للشباب من أجل التعامل مع تحديات الحياة.
Now, my second example is for a slightly younger crowd.
الآن، مثالي الثاني هو لمجموعة أصغر نسبياً.
And it's called "The 99."
وهو يسمى " التسعة وتسعين."
Now, these are the world's first Islamic superheroes.
الآن، هؤلاء أول أبطال مسلمين عالميين .
They were created by a Kuwaiti psychologist
وقد صنعهم طبيب نفساني كويتي
called Naif Al Mutawa.
يسمى نايف المطوع.
And his desire is to rescue Islam
ورغبته هي إنقاذ الإسلام
from images of intolerance,
من صور التعصب،
all in a child-friendly format.
بطريقة محببة للأطفال.
"The 99." The characters are meant to embody
"التسعة وتسعين,"هي شخصيات من المفترض أن تجسد
the 99 attributes of Allah:
أسماء الله التسعة وتسعين،
justice, wisdom, mercy, among others.
العدل، الحكيم، الرحيم، والبقية.
So, for example, there is the character of Noora.
لذا، على سبيل المثال، هناك شخصية نورا.
She is meant to have the power
ويُقصد أن يكون لديها المقدرة
to look inside people
على النظر لدواخل الناس
and see the good and bad in everyone.
وترى الطيب والخبيث في كل إنسان.
Another character called Jami
شخصية أخرى تسمى جامع
has the ability to create fantastic inventions.
لديه القدرة على صنع إبتكارات مذهلة.
Now, "The 99" is not just a comic book.
الآن، "التسعة وتسعين" ليست فقط كتاب كوميديا.
It's now a theme park.
إنها الآن منتزه.
There is an animated series in the works.
هناك سلسلة رسوم متحركة تحت التنفيذ.
And by this time next year,
وبحلول العام القادم
the likes of Superman and Wonder Woman
فأن شبيه سوبرمان وفتاة العجائب
will have joined forces with "The 99"
سينضمون لقوى "التسعة وتسعين"
to beat injustice wherever they find it.
لهزيمة الظلم حيثما يجدونه.
"The 99" and 4Shbab are just two of many examples
التسعة والتسعين و للشباب هما فقط مثالين من الكثير
of this sort of Islamic cross-cultural hybridization.
لهذا النوع من التهجين الثقافي الإسلامي .
We're not talking here about a clash of civilizations.
نحن لا نتحدث هنا عن صدام بين الحضارات.
Nor is it some sort of indistinguishable mash.
ولا نوع من الخليط الغامض.
I like to think of it as a mesh of civilizations,
أريد التفكير فيها كخليط بين الحضارات،
in which the strands of different cultures are intertwined.
الذي فيه فروعا لمختلف الثقافات المتشابكة.
Now, while 4Shbab and "The 99" may look new and shiny,
الآن، بينما تبدو "للشباب" و"التسعة وتسعين" جديدة وبراقة ،
there is actually a very long tradition of this.
ففي الواقع هناك تقليد قديم جداً لهذا.
Throughout its history, Islam has borrowed and adapted from other civilizations
عبر التاريخ إستعار الإسلام وتبنى أشياء جيدة من حضارات أخرى
both ancient and modern.
كلا القديمة والحديثة.
After all, it's the Quran which encourages us to do this:
وفوق كل هذا القرآن الذي يحثنا على فعل ذلك.
"We made you into nations and tribes
"وجعلناكم شعوباً وقبائل لتعارفوا"
so that you could learn from one another."
(ويمكنكم التعلم من بعضكم البعض)
And to my mind, those are pretty wise words,
وفي رأيي، أن تلك الكلمات حكيمة جداً،
no matter what your creed. Thank you.
بغض النظر عن عقيدتكم. شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)